<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>justmytwospence</title><link href="http://justmytwospence.github.com/pelican/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://justmytwospence.github.com/pelican/feeds/design-web.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://justmytwospence.github.com/pelican/</id><updated>2013-12-01T02:37:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Map-time at Stamen</title><link href="http://justmytwospence.github.com/pelican/map-time-at-stamen.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-12-01T02:37:00+01:00</updated><author><name>justmytwospence</name></author><id>tag:justmytwospence.github.com/pelican,2013-12-01:map-time-at-stamen.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;[dropcap]L[/dropcap]ast week, a classmate and I took a break from
coursework to attend one of the many great Meetup events that San
Francisco has to offer for data science practitioners. I’ve been pushing
myself to attend at least one data-centric Meetup every week, because
these events are one of the most amazing parts about going to school in
the same place where so many of the biggest names work. To be honest, I
believe that becoming a presence in the data science scene and meeting
the movers and shakers is equally if not more important than&amp;nbsp;coursework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I actually attended 3 meetups last week, one about D3.js at Trulia &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HQ&lt;/span&gt;,
one about &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GIS&lt;/span&gt; technologies and the Code for America &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HQ&lt;/span&gt;, and one about
mapping at Stamen &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HQ&lt;/span&gt;. I picked all three because they are relevant to a
geospatial data visualization that I am working on for my practicum at
AutoGrid, but the last one is what I’m going to talk a bit about,
because it was the most&amp;nbsp;hands-on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;The workshop took place at Stamen Design’s headquarters in the Mission&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="system-message"&gt;
&lt;p class="system-message-title"&gt;System Message: &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WARNING&lt;/span&gt;/2 (&lt;tt class="docutils"&gt;/Users/SpencerBoucher/pelican/content/map-time-at-stamen.rst&lt;/tt&gt;, line&amp;nbsp;26)&lt;/p&gt;
Line block ends without a blank line.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and was led by Eric Theise; you can see his beautiful/informative slides
(created using &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://lab.hakim.se/reveal-js/#/"&gt;reveal.js&lt;/a&gt;) here:
|  &lt;a href="#id1"&gt;&lt;span class="problematic" id="id2"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;_&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://erictheise.com/maptime_platform_slides/#/"&gt;http://erictheise.com/maptime_platform_slides/#/&lt;/a&gt;
|
|  Some useful Q&amp;amp;A happened on the Meetup event page as well:
|
` &amp;lt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.meetup.com/Maptime-SF/events/147110652/"&gt;http://www.meetup.com/Maptime-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SF&lt;/span&gt;/events/147110652/&lt;/a&gt;&amp;gt;`__&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.meetup.com/Maptime-SF/events/147110652/"&gt;http://www.meetup.com/Maptime-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SF&lt;/span&gt;/events/147110652/&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;|&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="system-message" id="id1"&gt;
&lt;p class="system-message-title"&gt;System Message: &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WARNING&lt;/span&gt;/2 (&lt;tt class="docutils"&gt;/Users/SpencerBoucher/pelican/content/map-time-at-stamen.rst&lt;/tt&gt;, line 26); &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="#id2"&gt;backlink&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Inline literal start-string without end-string.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was actually a two-part workshop, but it was relatively painless to
follow the instructions and get up to speed for the part &lt;span class="caps"&gt;II&lt;/span&gt;, so you
should really give it a shot even now if it looks&amp;nbsp;interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First we got postgres up and running on our machines. I have local
installations of MySQL, MongoDB, Hadoop and Hive up and running thanks
to our course in Distributed Databases, but our class didn’t have time
to get to postgres within a single credit hour. This, despite the fact
that our professor admits to postgres being the best database to use if
you have anything to say about&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, we populated our database with some data from OpenStreetMap. Mike
Migurski extracts data from &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OSM&lt;/span&gt; for major metropolitan areas on a
semi-regular basis, so we used the San Francisco data &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://metro.teczno.com/#san-francisco"&gt;available on his
web site&lt;/a&gt; via &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://wiki.openstreetmap.org/wiki/Osm2pgsql"&gt;osm2pgsql&lt;/a&gt;, a command-line utility that loads
OpenStreetMap data into PostgreSQL&amp;nbsp;databases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then we used &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.mapbox.com/tilemill/"&gt;TileMill&lt;/a&gt;, MapBox’s desktop application, to visualize our
newborn database. We discovered how remarkably easy it can be to create
vector layers for data contained in such a postGIS database using the
same old &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SQL&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CSS&lt;/span&gt; syntax you already know and love. Eric introduced
us to some sensible pre-baked &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/gravitystorm/openstreetmap-carto"&gt;CartoCSS boilerplate&lt;/a&gt; courtesy of Andy&amp;nbsp;Allen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, we used a nifty feature of TileMill to actually bake our own map
tiles and serve them up for use in our own maps. Note that if you want
to do this, you’ll need the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/mapbox/mbutil"&gt;mbutil command-line utility&lt;/a&gt;, not
currently mentioned in the slide&amp;nbsp;deck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not too shabby for 2 hours on a Wednesday night. Many thanks to the guys
at Stamen for hosting, especially Eric for all his work on the slides.
Not to mention the many other brilliant people who have made the tools
and resources that allow something this involved and grandiose to be
done on a laptop by someone who is still learning the ropes. Hands-on
workshops like this are one of the best ways to learn these
technologies. Case in point, I may not have ever stumbled across Mike or
Andy’s resources had I not been learning directly from people who are
intimately familiar with the practical ins and outs of digital&amp;nbsp;cartography.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Digital mapping is rapidly capturing my interest because of the
beautifully functional things one can do with it, and it seems like an
amazing time to be learning it, because the ecosystem is beginning to
really flourish. Looking forward to more&amp;nbsp;events!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- _: http://erictheise.com/maptime_platform_slides/#/ --&gt;
&lt;div class="system-message"&gt;
&lt;p class="system-message-title"&gt;System Message: &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WARNING&lt;/span&gt;/2 (&lt;tt class="docutils"&gt;/Users/SpencerBoucher/pelican/content/map-time-at-stamen.rst&lt;/tt&gt;, line&amp;nbsp;81)&lt;/p&gt;
malformed hyperlink target.&lt;/div&gt;
</summary><category term="cartography"></category><category term="maps"></category></entry></feed>